Guide to the Stephen Henry Bronson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Stephen Henry Bronson papers
1827-1881
MS 1282
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
(2 boxes)
The papers consist of the diaries and letters of Stephen Henry Bronson (with typescripts) and a diary of his father Henry Bronson (with typescript). The material documents the younger Bronson's three years of scientific and medical study in Paris, in addition to his European travels, 1867-1871. Henry Bronson's diary details his European voyage, 1839-1840.
Bronson, Stephen Henry, 1844-1880
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale University Medical Historical Library, 1980; gift of the Eli Whitney Museum, 1988.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The papers contain Stephen Henry Bronson's diaries (originals and typescripts) and letters (typescripts) to his parents, which date from 1867-1871 while Bronson was studying and traveling in Europe and Great Britain. Two diary volumes cover the entire period of Bronson's studies, 1867-1870, as well as an 1871 trip abroad, while the typescripts of letters cover the period from October 1867 - March 1869. The bi-weekly letters contain fuller descriptions of matters outlined in the daily diary entries.
Bronson travelled to Paris in order to pursue his scientific education, and the papers contain numerous references to his laboratory work in comparative anatomy at the Jardin des Plantes and with Milne Edwards. The papers also document the growth of Bronson's friendship with George Pouchet, his interests in paleontology, zoology, and other biological sciences, and his attendance at lectures in the medical sciences and natural history. The diaries record Bronson's attempts to learn French, and from the end of June, 1868 through February, 1870 all diary entries are in French. The diaries and letters also contain Bronson's observations on the national character, politics, scenery, museums, theatre, churches, and cultural events of France and Germany, and the cities of Prague, and Vienna. Diary entries for an 1871 trip note Bronson's travels in Great Britain.
In addition, the papers include a biographical sketch of Bronson, attributed to his father Henry Bronson, and a diary (original and typescript) kept by the elder Bronson on a trip to Europe in 1839-1840. This diary describes in great detail a long and arduous sea voyage from New York to Genoa and travels in Italy, France, Great Britain, and Ireland, including visits to Rome, the Vatican, Naples, and Pompeii.
Biographical / Historical
Stephen Henry Bronson was a graduate of the medical class of Yale College in 1866. He was a physician, founder of the New Haven Dispensary, and Yale College lecturer.
Anatomy, Comparative; Medical education; Medicine; Science; Voyages and travels; Europe -- Description and travel; France -- Description and travel; Great Britain -- Description and travel; Italy -- Description and travel; Paris (France) -- Description and travel; Diaries; Physicians; Bronson, Henry, 1804-1893; Bronson, Stephen Henry, 1844-1880; Edwards, Milne, 1800-1885; Pouchet, G. (Georges), 1833-1894
- Inventory, 1839-1871
  - Bronson, Stephen Henry
    - Biographical sketch (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Diaries
      - Originals, 1867-1871 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
      - Typescripts, 1867-1871 (Box 1, Folder 4-8)
    - Letters: typescripts, 1868-1869 (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
  - Bronson, Henry
    - Diary
      - Original, 1839-1840 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Typescript, 1839-1840 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Additional Material, 1827-1881, undated; Accession 1988-M-089; 0.25; (1 box)
  - Letters written by Stephen Henry Bronson, 1853-1876 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters to Sarah Lathrop Bronson (mother of Stephen Henry Bronson), 1827-1880, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters to and other papers of Henry Bronson, 1832-1881, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters to and checks of Nathan S. Bronson, 1852-1874, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters of others; other papers, 1827-1865 (Box 1, Folder 5)